Guide to The Rice Thresher records, 1962-2012 UA 354
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University The Rice Thresher records
1962-2012
1992-2003
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 354
8.5 Linear Feet
These records mostly include the photographs and negatives taken by "The Rice Thresher's" photographers, as well as research and issues pertaining to Rice University's student newspaper.
Biographical/Historical Note
In 1916, a group of nine students, chosen from the early literary societies, began to work on a bi-weekly newspaper. The new publication received its name from C. Harcourt Wooten '16. In a letter to President Edgar Odell Lovett, Wooten viewed a thresher as an object that "separates the good from the bad just as a publication should do."
As the first managing editor, William M. Standish published the first edition on January 15, 1916. With a circulation of over 500, "The Rice Thresher" was four pages long.
Published consistently since 1916, the student newspaper has grown in size and readership. As of 2014, the publication covers a wide variety of university events and issues, including faculty news, local Houston events, Rice theater, and sports.
--Quote taken from Sallyport April/May 1993
--Information taken from the Houston Chronicle, Dec. 9, 1915 and the Galveston News, Jan. 16, 1916
Scope and Contents Note
These records mostly include the photographs and negatives taken by "The Rice Thresher's" photographers, as well as research and issues pertaining to Rice University's student newspaper.
Conditions Governing Access
Some materials are restricted due to the sensitive information contained therein. Each restricted folder is labeled. Access to these records requires written permission from the Office of the Dean of Undergraduates. Materials will be restricted until 2064. Contact Woodson staff for instructions. woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Accruals Note
Additional materials are expected for this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The majority of the collection was donated by Dante Zakhidov, Miles Kruppa, and Kelley Callaway in 2014.
Index Terms
Subjects
College student newspapers and periodicals; Universities and colleges
Document Types
newspapers
- Series I: Documents, 181140
  - Athletics, 1990-1994, 2003-2005; 181142 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards, 1962-2012; 181143 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Campus Store, 2001; 181145 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Giant Floppy, n.d.; 181147 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gillis, Malcolm, 1994, 1998; 181148 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Health Services, 1992, 1998-1999; 181149 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Housing, 1997, 2004, n.d.; 181151 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Parking, 1992, 2002, n.d.; 181153 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Press Passes, 2002/2003, 2004/2005; 181154 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Relationship to the Student Association (Restricted), 1978-1998; 181155 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Rice Program Council, 2005-2006, n.d.; 181156 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Self-Scheduled Exams, 2004-2005; 181157 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Sexual Harassment/Faculty-Student Dating, 1989-1992; 181158 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Student Affairs Corrrespondence abou the Thresher (Restricted), 1982-2001; 181159 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Student Association, 1999, 2004-2006; 181165 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Student Calendar, 2003-2004; 181166 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Training, 1997, 2000, 2002, 2003; 181167 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Series II: Photographs, 181160
  - Baseball, 1990s; 181168 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Basketball, 1990s; 181169 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Beer Bike, 1990s-2000s; 181170 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Campus, 2000s; 181189 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Flipping Willy, 1988; 181222 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Football, 1990s; 181223 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Graduation, 1990s; 181224 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Houston, 1990s; 181225 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - KTRU, 1990s; 181226 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Owls, 1990s; 181229 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Rice University and Houston Visitors, 1980s-1990s; 181231 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Rice University People, A-E, 1980s-1990s; 181232 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Rice University People, F-L, 1980s-1990s; 181233 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Rice University People, M-R, 1980s-1990s; 181234 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Rice University People, S-Z, 1980s-1990s; 181235 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Rice University People, unknown, 1980s-1990s; 181236 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Student Life, 1980s-2000s; 181237 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Track and Field, 1990s; 181238 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - University Presidents, 1980s-1990s; 181239 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - WAC Championship Game - Women's Basketball, March 11, 2000; 181249 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Series III: Negatives, 181161
  - Subseries A: 1992/1993, 181251
    - Baseball, 181396 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Campus, 181397 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Club and Intramural Sports, 181398 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Football, 181399 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Houston, 181400 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Men's Basketball, 181401 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Men's Swimming, 181402 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Men's Tennis, 181403 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - O-Week, 181404 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Portraits, 181405 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Student Life, 181256 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Volleyball, 181406 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Women's Basketball, 181407 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Women's Tennis, 181408 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Subseries B: 1993/1994, 181258
    - Campus, 181381 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Men's Tennis, 181411 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Portraits, 181412 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Student Life, 181413 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Subseries C: 1994/1995, 181259
    - Academics, 181382 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Beer Bike, 181414 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Campus, 181415 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Student Life, 181383 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Volleyball, 181384 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Women's Tennis, 181416 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Subseries D: 1995/1996, 181270
    - Academics, 181417 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Baseball, 181418 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Campus, 181419 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Football, 181420 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Men's Basketball, 181421 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Miscellaneous Events, 181422 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Portraits, 181423 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - Student Life, 181385 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Swimming, 181424 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Track, 181425 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Volleyball, 181426 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Women's Basketball, 181427 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Subseries E: 1996/1997, 181271
    - Academics, 181386 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      General Note
      Includes images of Yasir Arafat, Madeleine Albright, and Richard Dawkins.
    - Baseball, 181387 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Beer Bike, 181388 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Campus, 181428 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Club and Intramural Sports, 181429 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Cross Country, 181430 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Football, 181389 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Graduation, 181390 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Houston, 181391 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Includes images of President Bill Clinton, Alanis Morisette, and Rage Against the Machine.
    - Men's Tennis, 181392 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - O-Week, 181393 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Portraits, 181431 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Still Life, 181432 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Student Life, 181433 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Volleyball, 181434 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Women's Basketball, 181435 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Women's Tennis, 181436 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Subseries F: 1997/1998, 181272
    - Baseball, 181437 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Beer Bike, 181438 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Campus, 181439 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Football, 181440 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Houston, 181441 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Men's Basketball, 181442 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Men's Tennis, 181443 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - O-Week, 181444 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Student Life, 181445 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Women's Tennis, 181446 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Volleyball, 181447 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Subseries G: 1998/1999, 181274
    - Academics, 181448 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Baseball, 181449 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Beer Bike, 181450 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - Campus, 181451 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Colleges, 181452 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Football, 181453 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Houston, 181454 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Men's Basketball, 181455 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Men's Swimming, 181456 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Men's Tennis, 181457 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Men's Track, 181458 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Portraits, 181459 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Student Life, 181460 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Volleyball, 181461 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Women's Basketball, 181462 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Women's Swimming, 181463 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Women's Tennis, 181464 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Women's Track, 181465 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Subseries H: 1999/2000, 181275
    - Academics, 181466 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      Includes images of Morris Dees and Robert MacNamara.
    - Baseball, 181467 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Beer Bike, 181468 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Campus, 181469 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Club and Intramural Sports, 181470 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Colleges, 181471 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Football, 181472 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Graduation, 181473 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Houston, 181474 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Includes images of concerts by Ben Harper and Henry Rollins.
    - Men's Basketball, 181475 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Men's Cross Country, 181476 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Men's Tennis, 181477 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - O-Week, 181478 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Portraits, 181479 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Student Life, 181480 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - Swimming, 181481 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Track and Field, 181482 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Volleyball, 181483 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Women's Basketball, 181484 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Women's Cross Country, 181485 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Women's Tennis, 181486 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Subseries I: 2000/2001, 181276
    - Academics, 181548 (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Includes images of former President of Ireland Mary McAleese and Jeff Bezos.
    - Baseball, 181549 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Beer Bike, 181550 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Campus, 181551 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Club and Intramural Sports, 181552 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Colleges, 181553 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Football, 181554 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Golf, 181555 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Houston, 181556 (Box 9, Folder 3)
      Includes images of a Pearl Jam concert.
    - Jackson, Liz - Football Player, 181557 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - KTRU, 181558 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Men's Basketball, 181559 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Men's Cross Country, 181560 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Men's Tennis, 181561 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Men's Track, 181562 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - O-Week, 181563 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Portraits, 181564 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Student Life (1 of 2), 181565 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Student Life (2 of 2), 181566 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Swimming, 181567 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Volleyball, 181568 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Women's Basketball, 181569 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Women's Cross Country, 181570 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Women's Tennis, 181571 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Women's Track, 181572 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Subseries J: 2001/2002, 181278
    - Academics, 181573 (Box 10, Folder 8)
      Includes images of President of Latvia Vaira Vīķe-Freiberga, Kay Bailey Hutchinson, James Burke, King Hussein bin Talal of Jordan, Alberto Gonzalez, Houston's Preparation for Terrorism press conference, Horton Foote, President of Algeria Abdelaziz Bouteflika, Alan Greenspan, C. Everett Koop, President of Mongolia Natsagiin Bagabandi, and the Houston Mayoral Debate.
    - Baseball, 181574 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Campus, 181575 (Box 10, Folder 10)
      Includes images of the Olympic Torch being run through the campus.
    - Colleges, 181576 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Club and Intramural Sports, 181577 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Esperanza, 181578 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Football, 181579 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Golf, 181580 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Houston, 181581 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Men's and Women's Track, 181583 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Men's Basketball, 181582 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Men's Tennis, 181584 (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - O-Week, 181585 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Portraits, 181586 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Putin, Vladmir, 181587 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Reaction to the September 11 Attacks, 181588 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Student Life (1 of 2), 181589 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Student Life (2 of 2), 181590 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Swimming, 181591 (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Volleyball, 181592 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Women's Basketball, 181593 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Women's Soccer, 181594 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Women's Tennis, 181595 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Subseries K: 2002/2003, 181279
    - Academics, 181596 (Box 12, Folder 8)
      Includes images of David Kopay, Colonel Laurence B. Wilkerson, Richard Holbrooke, Silvia Nasar, Lee Brown, and Gregory Stock.
    - Baseball, 2002/2003 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Beer Bike, 2002/2003 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Campus, 2002/2003 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Club and Intramural Sports, 181597 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Colleges, 181598 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Cross Country, 181599 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Football, 181600 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Golf, 181601 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Houston, 181602 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Men's Basketball, 181603 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Men's Tennis, 181604 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - O-Week, 181605 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Portraits, 181606 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Soccer, 181608 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Student Life, 181609 (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Swimming, 181610 (Box 13, Folder 13)
    - Volleyball, 181611 (Box 13, Folder 14)
    - Women's Basketball, 181612 (Box 13, Folder 15)
    - Women's Tennis, 181613 (Box 13, Folder 16)
  - Subseries L: n.d., 181607
    - Academics, 181614 (Box 13, Folder 17)
    - Baseball, 181615 (Box 13, Folder 18)
    - Beer Bike, 181616 (Box 13, Folder 19)
    - Campus, 181617 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Club and Intramural Sports, 181618 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Colleges, 181619 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Football, 181620 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Houston, 181621 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Men's Basketball, 181622 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Men's Tennis, 181623 (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 181624 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Portraits, 181625 (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Student Life, 181626 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Swimming, 181627 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - Track, 181628 (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - Volleyball, 181629 (Box 14, Folder 13)
    - Women's Basketball, 181630 (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Women's Tennis, 181631 (Box 14, Folder 15)
- Series IV: Slides, 181162
  - Student Life, 1998/1999; 181632 (Box 14, Folder 16)
  - Beer Bike, n.d.; 181633 (Box 14, Folder 17)
  - Campus, n.d.; 181634 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Houston, n.d.; 181635 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous, n.d.; 181636 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Student Life, n.d.; 181637 (Box 14, Folder 21)
- Series V: CDs and Floppy disk, 181163
  - CDs (57), 181638 (Box 15)
    These CDs consist of images, layouts, and news stories.
  - 8" floppy disk, 1982 (Box 15)
- Series VI: Oversize, 181164
  - Campus, 1990s; 181641 (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - Thresher Staff, 1990s; 181639 (Box 16, Folder 2)